welcome to eating with John Ricky so I'm
a cognitive psychologist and a cognitive
scientist at the University of Toronto I
study mindfulness and related phenomena
like insight flow mystical experience
and wisdom I have been practicing the
pasta meditation mat a contemplation and
Tai Chi Chuan and Chi cung for 29 years
and I've been teaching Metta and the
pasta and Tai Chi professionally for
almost twenty years so this is a
progressive course if you're joining us
for the first time you're welcome to
stay and then be teaching today and this
is going to be there sort of the fourth
basic principle I'm teaching so if you
want to catch up you can go back and
look at day one day two last Monday's
lesson to find the other teaching
lessons normally what will we do is
we've been doing teaching sessions on
Mondays and Thursdays but the schedule
is now going to change so this is hell
with the schedules now ready to come
teaching will only be on Mondays so
Monday will be the Dharma day I will
teach on Monday and then we will just
sit together do review and answer
questions Tuesdays Wednesdays Thursdays
and Fridays we will be meeting every
morning 9:30 est right every every
weekday morning Monday to Friday 9:30
est all right
so this is a progressive course again
you're welcome to stay but in order to
catch up and so you know what everybody
else is doing go see the previous
instruction videos and then you'll be
welcome to continue of course and you'll
have an understanding of what I'm
referring to what the other people are
practicing together so one more time
just to be clear for everybody because
we're trying where all of our schedules
and flux and start adding a little bit
of redundancy so this is remembered or
switch you to a new schedule we're only
meeting weekday mornings Monday to
Friday 9:30 est and we're having one
teaching class uh per week
Mondays alright so today we are doing in
teaching classes as our last Thursday
teaching class and what I want to teach
you today is the fourth of the core four
you find in order to properly setup your
mindfulness practice and this is finding
your focus as soon as I say finding your
focus as I mentioned what I talking
centering people immediately think of
concentration and think of the metaphor
concentrate so it's a concentric writer
and drawing my attention and I'm making
a tunnel and then I'm trying to stick it
and hold it on something and the way you
were previously taught to concentrate
was basically people yelling at you
pay attention concentrate so you've
developed this very we all have have
developed this very habitual automatic
sense of what it is to concentrate it's
you're slightly under threat and you've
got to bring your mind in you got to
hold it you got to stick it and hold it
on something and it's kind of this
enduring active will and when you get to
look at the Buddhist teaching he talks
about the Eightfold Path and one of them
is right concentration few things to
note about that because he tells us
there's right concentration that clearly
indicates that there's wrong
concentration concentration that's
actually not conducive to the
transformation and wisdom he was seeking
to teach people so that immediately
comes to mind what is right
concentration but before we can answer
that we have to understand what the word
right means we have to hear it correctly
because we tend to hear right and we
tend to hear it in terms of
righteousness and like it's a mortal
thing like doing good that's not the
kind of right that is met it's closer to
right-handedness it means dexterous it
means skillful so we have to have the
appropriately skilled kind of
concentration now a good way of
understanding what this is is to take a
look at some of the week's great work
done by onliner she was one of the first
people to work on mindfulness in the
West she wrote a book and the eighties
actually called mindfulness and to also
look at the research about what kinds of
attention are actually conducive to
insight and enhance self-regulation
because that's actually
what we're after it turns out that
that's sort of hard fixed-focus what's
called it heart focus the way an aligner
does isn't really good for insight and
self-regulation let let's bring up a
contrast she contrasts between hard
focus and soft vigilance so I'm going to
do something here let's let's do it
let's do the old way first I'm gonna
hold up my finger concentrate
concentrate on my finger concentrate
concentrate concentrate as you notice
that is both challenging and boring at
the same time and it's not doing very
much too loudly so hard focus not good
let's replace it with something else
okay now look at my finger again notice
that my finger is slightly bent that
there are three sections to it that it's
actually not white that there is you
know a sort of pinkish tinge in some
areas you might even see it if you're
looking closer there's some hairs
towards the base with my finger and my
in fingers position is certainly
slightly shifting around because my my
hand can't be completely stable now
notice the difference there notice how
you were able to stay with my finger you
were able to stay involved with my
finger this is called soft vigilance
soft vigilance please remember the word
vigilance we're going to talk about it
again so we're doing two things at once
here we're teaching you how to
appropriately concentrate but I'm also
introducing you to this idea of
vigilance or watchfulness and we're
going to come back to that when we talk
about the five factors of including
mindfulness so soft vigilance is this
exploratory thing what you're what
you're trying to do is constantly renew
your interest in what you're paying
attention to rather than just a hard
fixation you're trying to constantly
renew your interest in what you're
paying attention to that's why it's a
soft flowing vigilance and touchy trauma
talk about having Tiger eyes these are
eyes that are doing that soft vigilance
constantly flowing over your
opponent when you're sparring with them
typically in fact what people do in in
conflict situations self-defense
situations is they hard fix they fix on
the person's face
you shouldn't by the way a fix on
people's face you should be paying
attention to their shoulders or when
people talk to victims who have been
held up like a gunpoint
the victims can describe the gun really
well and they can't describe the face of
the assailant
we don't want hard fixation we want
tiger eyes of the mind we want a soft
flowing vigilance because this is
actually conducive to insight this is
conducive to self-regulation this is
conducive to self transformation think
about renewing your interest think about
what the word interest means it comes
from two Latin words interests it means
to be within something inter si to be
within so what you're constantly trying
to do is renew your interest constantly
find something new about it explore it
look around
think about concentration as a where as
what you're trying to do is get one
moment of noticing to stitch together to
engender to lead you into another moment
of noticing which leads you into another
moment of noticing not just passive
holding right right but this act did
exploratory ongoing noticing so what you
want to do is you want to think of
concentration as creating a momentum of
mindfulness right with that one moment
of not just being sort of attached to
the thing but in it president true and
with it not just not just present to it
but present through and with it right
so what you want to do is create that
continuity and you see what I keep doing
with my hands because the metaphor the
metaphor that's used right it's to
become like a self rolling wheel you
instead of instead of instead of
concentration being like this right hold
my mind from the outside and push my way
through can you and it takes time to
shift so I'm describing this easily I'm
learning that habit and learning when
I'm talk
but takes time requires patience
requires preventing yourself but you
want to shift from her and pushing to
wait I can get interested in this and
that takes me deeper and deeper and
deeper and the fact that you've already
learned how to flow helps this helps
this there's actually continuity between
finding your flow and finding your focus
ok so what's an exercise for getting
this sense of concentration again let's
frame this correctly you're not going to
instantly go bang into this we've had a
whole lifetime of concentrate now you're
trying to enter the stream as the
Buddhist metaphor is you're trying to
find this current that renews itself and
flow with it it will take time and
practice and diligence to shift over to
soft vigilance so what we do is an
exercise is the following we do
everything we need to do we find our
Center you find our route we find our
flow we start just a basic meditation
basic the pasta in then we move to the
exercise and the exercise is the
following it's called counting your
breath now some of nutritionists use
counting your breath as the main
meditative focus there's versions of Zen
that do that that's not quite what we're
doing here
and secondly you can't frame this and
the way we're automatically framing it
is it is we're four oh no right you know
if I try to count my breath I won't be
able to count it for very long we'll get
distracted and we're using the wrong
sense
the wrong sense of right concentration
we're using that sort of moral judgment
sense what we're after is instead no no
I'm trying to develop a increasingly
evolving refined skill ok so what we do
is we do the following in and out and we
count one now what does the counting
look like if and this is I can't be in
your head yeah I'm sure you're grateful
for that as am i right
so if
majority of your attention center stage
the mic of your mind right is on your
breath he counted it there can be stuff
going on around here loner murmuring the
background and things footing but if the
majority of your attention is center
stage on your breath right he panted but
when you're Jin you want the monkey mind
and the center of the attention moves
elsewhere then you reduce the count back
to zero and start again and this is
where people go oh no oh no oh no I
can't do this alone
oh we get to one or two that's not the
point of this the point of the counting
is not to try and push yourself to a
longer account that's why I spent that
time to really try to see which the
point is just try and as much as you can
fall into the kind of flowing attention
you're doing right when you're doing the
posture but here's the difference try to
continually renew your interest in your
breath and finding your flow helps
though what's changing what's different
what haven't I noticed about my
sensations and when you notice that the
count has made it past 2:00 or 3:00
you'll lose it below and then you want
to reset and that's fine that is fine
but then when you catch yourself about
to leave your breath try to remember as
quickly as you can okay what did that
feel like what did it feel like to be in
the street that's the whole point of the
counting the point of accounting is to
give you a moment of remember sati is to
remind that's that that's that probably
word the Sanskrit word for mindfulness
it ultimately needs to remind to
remember so remind yourself remember
what was it like to be in the street
what was like when I was sort of flowing
with my breath rather than pushing
myself along okay no again you're gonna
you're gonna have to be making an effort
either and it's gonna take time to shift
from the automatic habituated style of
concentration but this is what the
exercise is designed to do is designed
to give you oh that's what it feels like
well that's what it feels like oh that's
what it feels like oh that's and you're
gonna have to do this a thousand times
that's what it feels like oh that's what
it feels like that's what it feels like
okay now I can't talk you through this
exercise because I can't be in your head
so what we'll do is the following will
do the following
they'll be silenced for a very long time
because you're going to be centering
routine flowing okay and then at some
point to remind you because we could
sometimes people forget when I taught
this in the past right I'll say okay
count your breath we'll do that for a
better count your breath so two things
follow your breath in that renewing
interest when you're distracted first do
tooth before you even note the
distraction note oh right when you
realize oh I'm distracted try to
remember what did it feel to be in the
stream note that is fraction and then
when you return to your breath don't
just return fix it return renewing your
interest trying to inhabit your your
breath involve yourself in it not just
present to it but present through it and
with it and in it and then after a while
I'll say okay stop counting your breath
and just follow your breath go back to
basic for pasta if you need to you might
need to sort of reconnect with your
sense of flow or maybe even a quick
check on your Center you've written your
flow then try and follow your breath
follow your breath trying with that you
know focal and peripheral don't lose
your flow here's your focal in your
field awareness right but where it's
focal try to constantly renew your
interest when you're distracted label
your distraction with an ING word and
then when you return your breath return
in a sense of trying to renew try to
engage in a process of more active
exploratory noticing okay so that's what
we're going to do one more time don't
get into judgment about the count
that is not its point this is not about
righteousness this is about that gentle
correction in befriending yourself when
you're trying to acquire a skill you
don't yet have okay we will begin when I
say begin remember to find the core
remember to find your Center your root
of your flow first begin
you can count in your breath
not a return to following your breath in
the Posada
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to intubate what you
call today in your practice with your
everyday consciousness and cognition so
let's look at some questions this is
from Keira Krueger I seem to start
become a practice especially when I
noticed worrying is that normal
what's the best way to handle this yes
that is normal you're probably going
through what's called parasympathetic
rebound so your autonomic nervous system
has two parts to it the sympathetic and
the parasympathetic the sympathetic
arouses you energizes you gets you ready
to fight or to flee your sympathetic
system relaxes you calms you down and
they push and pull on each other to
constantly come competing and if you've
had a lot of worry that's really putting
your sympathetic system like this it's
really pulling really really pulling and
so the parasympathetic pulling is
pulling more and more harder and harder
to try and make it come back to Center
and then when you start to meditate
especially if you noticed whirring it
step aside from it this this way and
this way your parasympathetic system is
responsible for it posture your
breathing and your tearing and so what
happens is you over tear you slouch a
bit you have a release right and you
your things that come to mind that were
normally being inhibited and so you can
cry so parasympathetic rebound is quite
common amongst people especially if
they're under stress and they're
noticing a lot of worrying in their
meditation so it's very normal
it will pass with time especially as you
start to practice mindfulness throughout
your day not just in your city because
this will help to get these more
balanced throughout the day just try to
note the crying it's not anything to be
really worried about note the crying and
then return to your breath now again if
something else is coming up
no stuff from the past a sense of trauma
or abuse that's a different issue and
you need to talk to a therapist about
them is the interest that you're trying
to cultivate while coming back to your
breath similar to the interest you have
while playing a piece of music you enjoy
exactly Thank You Leo that's exactly
right
that constant right that's the flow
interest exactly exactly
very well set Leo Nicholas again hello
Nicholas I'll respond to your emails by
the way do we do the remembering
noticing returning renewed interest
during the actual past and part of the
meditation or only during defining your
focus part yeah just do that they're
remembering part like trying to remember
what the continuity felt just in the
into counting your breath but in your
regular for pasta go back to you know
noting with an ING word returning but
when you return to your breath renew the
interest that's always going to be part
of your practice renew your interest try
it and try to remember that sense of
continuity of flow
Karima is it okay to not follow breath
up into the head
I'm not
on your breath just in your in your body
in your torso the problem with and this
is why I'm a little bit hesitant I don't
wanna
following the breath and those breathing
in the head tends to make people
lightheaded and get them into their
headspace a little too much disciple of
raw do you advise setting up an
environment that is virtually no history
before meditation or should one try to
make use of the surrounding ambient
noise to concentrate initially initially
like say for maybe the time of this
course set up a very quiet environment
and in fact everybody try to go and
meditate in the same place making sure
it's quiet softly let ask people to not
disturb you as much as possible right
you may you might need to new use
earplugs if you have them initially I
try to also set up a couple of practices
remember we talked about encoding
specificity that will help train you to
get into the state ringabel
lighted candle lights of incense these
will help you but once the course is
over then then it will it will talk
about how to shift okay Nick Kennedy
hello again Nick stuff knows today
really intensifies the sensation of
blood flow and pulse can you elaborate
on mouth breathing yeah so when you have
a stuff nose I put your tongue you just
on your palate where you would say T or
B like that
hold it there motion your tongue and
then try to feel the airflow coming over
your tongue because that will help keep
it how helpful also heat your throat
moist and it also will keep your throat
open my breath and abdomen and trying to
expand to chest and shoulders I find
myself jumping quite rapidly all over
the place so returning back to focusing
only on the abdomen is that okay
yes for now that's okay maybe maybe once
or twice a week try bringing it up just
into the chest just a little bit maybe
not all the way just that probative
erosion until you make your way there
don see do you recommend we go through
every aspect routing flowing in every
sit or do you think it's acceptable
focus on just one or two aspects
centering concentration and a greater
set I would recommend always doing the
core for and in the order I've taught
you you want to try and get them to
constantly together to interpenetrate so
that they become
one thing for you so you just center
root flow and get into soft vigilance
you want that to become like a consulted
unified second nature too so everyone
thank you for joining as always thank
you amar and Jason after your help
reminder that we're switching the
schedule there will be no six anymore on
Saturday there will be a set tomorrow we
will only meet on weekdays 9:30 EST and
we will have one teaching class per week
one Dharma day and that will be Monday
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video and also
you'll find lots of videos on my channel
some of you have already been commenting
on that that you will find helpful about
how to situate this practice into a
broader ecology of practices and overall
orientation cultivating wisdom
cultivating an adaptive connectivity to
an unfolding and complex reality so I
think that's all we need to do for today
please remember continuity of practice
more important than quantity there's no
reason not to sit at all there is no
reason not to sit at all hey carry one
keep practicing and I'll see you
tomorrow thank you for your time and
attention